Guide to the Henry Salem Hubbell papers, 1800-1975.
Hubbell, Henry Salem papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Henry Salem Hubbell papers, 1800-1975.
1955
Henry Salem Hubbell, 1869-1949.
5 cubic ft.
Correspondence, research and lecture notes, catalogs, newspaper clippings, scripts, theatrical programs, photographs, audiotapes, manuscripts, and other papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence and other papers of Henry Salem Hubbell, a portrait artist and educator.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Henry Salem Hubbell, a portrait artist, was the head of the Carnegie Institute of Technology School of Painting and Decoration in Pittsburgh, 1918-1921.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letters (1897-1907) from Hubbell, when an art student in Paris, Etaples, and Madrid, and from his wife, (Nellie) Rose Strong Hubbell, largely to his benefactor Mrs. Lydis Avery Coonley Ward; correspondence (1891-1944) between Hubbell and his family; research and lecture notes; correspondence, catalogs, and newspaper clippings concerning his paintings and exhibitions; scripts, programs, and notices of amateur plays in which he was either an actor or set designer; and photographs of himself and his paintings, studios, homes, and family. Also, tape recordings, notes, and correspondence of his son, Henry Willard Hubbell, concerning his father's life and work; typescripts and proofs of the journals, plays and short stories, articles, and verse written by Mrs. Hubbell; photocopies and typescripts of papers dealing with the history and genealogy of the Hubbell (Hubbels, Hubbel), Gleason, Rockwell, and related families (1800-1940); and proposals concerning the role of art education at the University of Miami.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Hubbell, Henry Salem, 1869-1949.; Gleason family.; Hubbel family.; Hubbell family.; Hubbell, Henry Willard.; Hubbell, Rose Strong.; Hubbels family.; Rockwell family.; Ward, Lydis Avery Coonley.; Carnegie Institute of Technology. School of Painting and Decoration.
Subjects:
Amateur theater.; Art.; Education in art.; Literature.; Painting.
Form and Genre Terms:
Genealogies.; Lecture notes.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Photographs of portraits
  - #68: Secretaries of Interior Department - research material including list of the secretaries from 1849-1889 and vital statistics of each; pencil sketches of facial characteristics of several of the secretaries; correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - #70-89: Correspondence, newspaper clippings, 1928-1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - #91-103: Correspondence, newspaper clippings, magazine cover, 1928-1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - #109-118: Correspondence, newspaper clippings, 1927-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - #123-193: Correspondence, newspaper clippings, 1935-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - #133-154: Correspondence, newspaper clippings, 1910-1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - #158-196: Correspondence, newspaper clippings, 1928-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - #197-200: Correspondence, newspaper clippings, 1935-1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - #209-223: Correspondence, newspaper clippings, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous correspondence
  - A-B correspondence, 1933-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - W. Bingham 2nd, 1933-1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Copies of Account of Proceedings and Receipt and Release in the matter of the settlement of Trust Funds for Mr. and Mrs. Hubbell set up by W. Bingham 2nd, April 1949, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Alice Gleason Bowman correspondence, newspaper clippings, 1937-1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - C correspondence, 1903-1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Carnegie Tech. Papers (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
  - Sarah Coonley Davies, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - E-F correspondence, 1898-1944 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ruth Marie Field, 1937-1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ruth Marie Field, 1943-1949 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - G-H correspondence, 1909-1944 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rose Strong Hubbell, 1905-1935 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Miscellany, 1934-1942 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Correspondence, 1891-1913 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Family correspondence - original and t.s. copies, 1895-1903 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - original and t.s., 1901 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - original and t.s., 1902 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - original and t.s., 1923-1926 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - April 29, 1901-May 2, 1902, 1901-1902 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - June 29, 1902-April 2, 1903, 1902-1903 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - May 11,-September 5, 1903, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - October 31, 1903-July 25, 1905, 1903-1904 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - October 9, 1904-March 24, 1907, 1904-1907 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Family letters, 1916-1923 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Family letters, 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Family letters, 1925-1939 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Family letters, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Family letters, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Family letters, 1936-1946 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Mrs. O. W. Hubbell letters, 1890-1906 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Letters to Willard Hubbell, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - I correspondence, primarily Harold Ickes, 1928-1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lyons Case, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - M correspondence, 1939-1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - N, O, P correspondence, 1925-1949 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - R, S, W, Z correspondence, 1925-1948 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Booth Tarkington Letters, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Odds and Ends, 1886, 1904-1949 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Louise Orwig Letters, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Exhibitions of Hubbell works (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Re: portrait of Mrs. J. G. Gehring (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence re: paintings; miscellaneous correspondence, 1896-1960 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence re: photos of paintings (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - (Removed from "Correspondence re: photos of paintings") (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Other papers
  - "By the Fireside" (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper clippings re: photos of paintings (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Odds and Ends (Box 3, Folder 17-19)
  - Newspaper clippings (fragile) (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
  - Odds and Ends (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Odds and Ends: real estate, will, miscellany (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Re: art gallery proposals, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Rec'd 8-1-72 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miscellany (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Lecture notes? (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
  - Florida State Guide - dummy, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Hubbell Book" (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
  - "Henry" mss. by Rose Strong Hubbell (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - If I Could Fly by R. H. Hubbell - proof, reviews, clippings (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Newsclippings - "Quacky Doodles" by R. S. Hubbell (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "It Happened to Us" Memoirs of an Artist's Wife by R. S. Hubbell (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Carnegie Tech School of the Arts - R. S. Hubbell (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "The Aulis Difficulty" by Maurice Baring (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "The Boy Comes Home" by Milne [?] (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hubbell guest book, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Miscellany rec'd 1975 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - K. Morris poster, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Notes (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - Transcripts of tapes B,C,D - recordings #2-8, p. 25-53 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Transcripts of tapes B,C,D - recordings #2-8, p. 1-24 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Miscellany (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Hubbell as actor (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photographs - Cornelia Gray Lunt, Hubbell Houses, and Cornell University, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photographs from album (nos. 1-24) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Photographs from album (nos. 25-55) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, 1918-1926 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Photographs at Miami, 1924-1949 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Artistic Anatomy of The Human Figure by Henry Warren, 1886 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Address book, ca. 1907 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Rec'd 3-18-68 (see separate page) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Rec'd 6-21-68 (see separate page) (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Rec'd 9-23-70 (see separate page) (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Rec'd 2-71 (see separate page) (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Photographs and negatives of: sketches of human anatomy at Carnegie Tech; paintings; Hubbell and Hubbell family; Strong family; friends; France and Spain; Chicago; also, scrapbook pages (Box 7)
  - Photographs of portraits and of paintings other than portraits (Box 8)
  - Scrapbooks A and B (Box 9)
  - Printed material including art exhibit catalogs (Box 10)
  - Anatomical sketches (Mapcase-folder 1-2)
  - Tape recordings made by Willard Hubbell of descriptive notes, personal comments, and reminiscences relating to the Hubbell papers